[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software hey this is Jeremy Jung for
software engineering radio today I'm
talking to woter he's the author of The
Creative programmer and a PhD researcher
at the faculty of engineering techn
technology at KU Len his research
focuses on non-technical skills in
software engineering education and he
primarily is targeting creative problem
solving woter welcome to software
engineering radio hi thanks for having
me really excited to be here you worked
in industry for over a decade why moved
to Academia what was the turning point
there that's a good question the turning
point for me was as a as a coach and
Technical lead I also did a lot of job
interviews and we onboarded seniors we
onboarded Juniors and most of the time
the people that were
new after a few months they were
technically more than proficient enough
to to join the daily development cycle
but we noticed that things like for
instance problem solving skills
communication skills teamwork how to
solve a problem in multiple ways and
those were things that were really
lacking and we didn't really have a good
way to teach them how to do these things
because they were really difficult for
us to identify in the first place so
those were the things that really
interested me so how do you do it in
multiple ways and that was one of the
reasons why eventually I left in
industry and I have been researching the
exact topic for the last five years in
combination with teaching so that's that
was a really interesting combination one
of the things you said in your book is
you felt like software seems to be
doomed to
fail that's a good way to start a book
right yeah so like what did you mean by
that and and what were the the biggest
problems you saw I'm not really sure
what I meant by that but somehow every
time we try to develop a big piece of
software it all ends it always ends in a
big ball of mud or nearly always I've
been on I've been working on more than
20 different projects over the course of
the last 17 years I think and the ones
that were really successful I think I
can go on one hand
so and of course there are multiple
reasons why budget is one of the reasons
mismanagement is one of the reasons but
also miscommunication and Mis
collaboration is one of the reasons
hiring them wrong people near shuring
and not knowing how to handle near
sharing is one of the reasons technical
dep and ignoring technical issues is one
of the reasons also one of the big
reasons in my view but that's of course
really difficult to to scientifically
back is not knowing how to approach a
problem given a tight set of constraints
we always approach a problem the same
way once we noticed okay this is how it
works then the next problem we just
apply the previous pattern because we
know this worked oh no it doesn't no I
don't really know what to do so you need
to come up with multiple ways to get
around that and that was one of the
things that I I've been
researching so let's talk a little more
about examples of those kinds of
constraints what were things that you
saw both from your research or just
talking to people in Industry well if
you if you're referring to constraints
specifically then perhaps one of the
good examples is working with Legacy
software we all still daily touch it and
nobody really wants to do it we could we
can debate the definition of legacy
software but it mostly boils down to
being afraid to change something because
something will break but you don't
really know when it will and you usually
notice it two weeks too late when the
thing has been shipped in production and
uh of course there are no tests for it
so how do you approach something like
that for instance let's say an old
Cobble software or Visual Basic software
where things like uh unit testing and uh
PA program in and scrum and the the new
agile techniques weren't usually that
common back in the day we could still
apply those principles to the Legacy
part of the software and most of the the
people who approach that they just say
no we can't do that well in effect you
can and there is a for instance there's
a Visual Basic 6 xunit toolkit which
allows you to write unit tests that's
possible it's not a lot of fun but you
can still apply the mod techniques using
the old so software development tools
and another project I've worked with
lots of domain logic was written in
store procedures in Oracle in the
database itself that's of course a
really really bad
decision but we we couldn't change that
on time and we had to change something
within let's say a week or two weeks so
you can really refactor out everything
but after a bit of searching we found
out that there was a way to unit or
integration test one of those
procedures so you have to be open to the
idea of applying modern techniques to
the old part of the software While most
people and the team just said let's just
roll with it and change stuff and we'll
see what we end up with and most of the
time that means breaking
things it sounds like this may be a
combination of facing a constraint but
then not restricting yourself based on
what used to be and maybe that's I don't
know what you would call call that maybe
it's like a form of curiosity a form of
thinking that hey even though this is
old technology that doesn't mean I have
to do everything also in the old way
yeah I think it's both in the book
itself we discussed seven distinct
themes of creative problem solving and
well they're distinct but they're still
highly interconnected right so curiosity
and critical thinking are two different
domains and constraint based thinking is
a third one and everything is highly
interconnected which means a lack of
iCal thinking of just saying this is all
software we can't really change
anything results in taking a certain
path which could have being a better
path but you just don't really see it or
don't want to see it so it's a
combination of still being curious hm
what if we could do something like that
and asking the right critical questions
challenging your colleagues and saying
maybe this can be done within the time
frame so yeah it's it's a combination of
of different things like like everything
in this world of course yeah and and
that makes sense to me the the
combination of critical thinking
curiosity the constraints your book
specifically is called the the creative
programmer and I I think the word
creative can mean a lot of different
things to different people or they're
it's just fuzzy right when when you say
be more creative what does that even
mean so yeah that's I think that's the
biggest problem if you use vague words
like creativity and most of the time if
I ask my wife what do you think is
creativity about then she'll mention
something like colored pencils or art or
design or things like that something
visually interesting something novel it
depends on the domain of course you're
in and we're interested in creativity in
the domain of software engineering and
not just in art and if you take a look
at the existing research of cognitive
psychologists who have been researching
creativity for the last 50 years there's
a lot of evolution in the definition of
course there are hundreds of definitions
but the general Trend was that
creativity is three things it's got to
be original it's got to be applicable at
the task at hand and it's got to be
qualitative so it has to maintain a
certain degree of Standards but that
doesn't really take context into account
right so this creativity is much more
than just those three things so the
researchers have evolved from that basic
definition to a more social cultural one
which means
in practice it simply means creativity
is if someone says it's creative then
it's creative so it's a social verdict
right creativity and isolation means
nothing I can't say for myself that I'm
creative I can only say it because I'm
comparing my things with the things
someone else made and if I never done
something like that before then I'm
creative even though you think it's not
creative at all because it's been done a
hundred of times so there's a lot of
different things to take into account
when when we are approaching creativity
right but the thing we're most
interested in of course in software
engineering is solving problems so we're
not just being creative because we want
to be creative or for the fun of it we
we're being creative to solve something
to so creativity is used as a tool not
just as a thing in itself which is also
fine of course it can also be something
really interesting but you have to take
the context into
account and sometimes when you hear the
word creativity in the context of of
software someone might write some
software that seems
really interesting or unique but is very
difficult for other people to understand
but they they say like oh but it's very
creative right so I wonder how
you distinguish between good creativity
and uh maybe not so much then we use
creativity with the air quotes
creativity no yeah that's of course that
depends on on the team you're in if the
world team thinks that's a good way to
approach the coding problem then who am
I to judge that that's not creative at
all if you move from one team to the
other and you think you're not creative
at all but in the next team you're
applying a principle you have been
applying before and everyone thinks wow
that's that's an interesting way to
approach a problem that's really
creative and you're like no it's not
I've been doing that for like five years
but the people surounding you and in the
new team they they weren't really aware
of
it so I think that depends it's not
really that interesting to you know to
stand still too much about and to
discuss what you would think creativity
is really about it's I think one of the
difficulties of course is pinpointing
the definition and we as researcher
we're also not really sure which of the
published definitions should we use as a
starting point to research this this top
in software engineering right in
software engineering so what we did was
actually just go to developers go to
different companies in different
countries and we surveyed them we just
asked them what do you think creativity
means as a software engineer as a
software developer and the result is
those seven domains so after lots of
processing the data processing um
identifying shared and key Concepts the
results is actually the seven check in
this book and maybe just really briefly
you could say what those seven are yeah
sure sure so the first one is called
technical knowledge uh which means you
have to have some sort of technical
standard to be able to be a little bit
creative in it as an example for
instance if I'm a python programmer
chances are high I can speak Python and
I can be a little bit creative in my
pythonic code if I've never programmed
before then it's really difficult for me
to be creative at Python Programming if
I ask my wife right now can you write
something creative and original and
python I don't really think that's going
to be interesting to put in production
right so you have to have some sort of
technical Baseline knowledge is an
important part of creative problem
solving the next one is called
communication or collaboration which
means that like I said before creativity
doesn't really happen in isolation it's
the most interesting Solutions happen in
conjunction with other people and those
other people by preference should be a
heterogenous group not not like-minded
people so you can have this interesting
discussion with a with someone from for
instance biology or someone from
architecture and they might say oh we
doing things like this and then we as a
software engineer would say hm that's
interesting perhaps we can apply this
pattern in software engineering and then
you have results like asynchronous
programming and like a service buses
things like that all originated beyond
the scope of software engineering so
that's communication or
collaboration the third one is
constraints we already talked about that
the fourth one is critical thinking
that's also briefly mentioned critical
thinking and then curiosity getting out
of your comfort zone not being afraid to
ask questions motivation to have that
creative urge to keep on trying to
tackle that specific problem instead of
giving up and next we have creative a
creative state of mind with a state of
mind I mean being in a certain flow flow
is a a really popular word right now you
know having those aha moments the short
thoughts and doing something with with
ideas and and Def factoring or
reiterating on on those that's a that's
what I call a creative state of mind
which can be personal or can also be a
corporate state of mind we can we can
talk about that in a second and then
lastly you have practical creative
techniques if you don't know how to zoom
out on a problem and approach it like a
bird on a top down View and then zoom
zoom in back on the the method you're
you're writing to get an overview and
then say oh yeah okay no I need to write
this line because in another component
it it's been done that way if you don't
know how to do these techniques then of
course your creative input is going to
be limited so those are the the seven
main themes of what I call being a
creative programmer and you talked a
little bit about this earlier where you
have this questionnaire where you
evaluate someone's State as a creative
programmer and I wonder if you can give
some examples of of ways people fill out
that test and and how it caused them to
reflect and identify the areas where
they can improve or identify areas that
were problems in their organization yeah
yeah the test was developed with uh
software engineering students and higher
education in mind but it it's also
really interesting to take that test as
a as an engineer in in the industry why
because some of the questions are like
during this or this or this project I
asked help from colleagues that's a
really stupid question of course for
students most of the students would
answer yes I consulted my my friends who
are also students next to me and then
you have the next question which is you
did did you consult your peers the
teachers did you ask when when stuck did
you ask something and most of those
students and we learned are afraid to
ask questions because when they approach
a professor or an assistant like I was
they think they're going to be evaluated
and they think if I ask a question I'm
going to look stupid and they will know
I don't really know what I'm talking
about but that's a wrong way to approach
something because if they ask a question
perhaps I can chime in and say hm did
you think about this or this or this and
then they are like oh that's interesting
maybe we could approach it like that I
helped them open up a different Pathway
to the solution and the next time they
approach a similar similar problem
perhaps they will think about hm maybe
we should do it like this I know the
people in the industry are more used to
doing things like that but those reflect
kind of questions are really interesting
because most of the time we're not
really given the time to think about the
way we approach problems it's just 10
minutes or like 50 minutes and it's in
context of a specific project you're
working on at the end it'll also say uh
regarding collaboration or regarding
curiosity or regarding your state of
mind you're doing really a great job or
you're doing not so well here are a few
to help you improve or get
unstuck and in issuing those those tests
to students did you get any feedback
specifically about like oh I I wasn't
doing this but when I took the test I
realized there were all these things
that I I could have been doing that sort
of thing yeah that that was exactly the
response yeah and that was really good
because uh I was happy I thought maybe
they have learned
something but we did Issue the test with
I think last year students first year
students and third grade I'm not really
sure again but it's not a longitudial
study so one of the follow-up studies
could be a a more interesting one like
doing this again within a few years
again within a few years again within a
few years and then compare the results
did they learn something because if I
take a test and if there's a reflective
question that makes me think hm perhaps
I could apply it next time after 5
minutes I might have forgotten about it
so in the end you don't really learn
anything so the most interesting thing
is after like a year or like a few years
or perhaps if they graduated and they
they went to Industry and after a few
years in that company did they think
back about the the things in this test
and I'm a bit pessimistic in that regard
I think the answer is going to be no and
in that case they nowadays they have
really easy access to my to my research
they just got be read read the book
again and sort of related to that in
your book you talk about the concept of
I think you called them dream teams
where you you're on a team that creates
this stimulating environment
where everybody is is making each other
better making each other think about
things they otherwise wouldn't have
thought
about what were some of the constants
across teams like that like what was
different about those teams that that
got people into this creative state of
mind there's a couple of different
things I think one of them is is the
environment you're in by that I mean the
physical environments some companies
they really take an effort to create an
a nice place to work an interesting
place where as a developer you're happy
and you're content to get to the office
office well of course postco most of the
people are are working from home so
that's that's their their responsibility
to uh get a nice desk and a few plans
and things like that but besides that
besides feeling at home and feeling
relaxed and then doing the work I think
it's the Relentless curiosity and the
endless drive to keep on going and to
motivate each other and keep motivating
each other even when the things get
tough and the tough gets going that was
a constant factor and that's something
you don't really often see and in some
interviews that I've read and some
interviews I've also conducted software
Engineers say the stars must have
aligned for this team
to to to be to make it to into existence
uh because this was one of a one of a
kind opportunity I've also worked in a
few I've I've been lucky enough to to be
in a really interesting and really cool
team
uh and there was so much learning from
and to and and everyone was motivated to
go to work and the the next project I
was on was with another team and it was
completely opposite so that so it's
really tough to I pinpoint and to
identify these are the the the things
you need to have a super performing team
and the and the dream team for instance
there's a lot of research on that and
the results of the research search
depending on the paper are completely
different so
yeah yeah so we're we're still stuck
just hoping the star is a lion anytime
we join a new
team there's a a few a few shared things
like you know that Curiosity and the
motivation and but of course if you have
a boss who yells at you then you're not
really that motivated to to come to work
each day so these are the the obvious
things that I guess everyone will
mention but the less obvious things I
think we still trying to identify and
and and dig into that I mean you gave
the obvious example if you have yeah an
abusive boss or something like that of
course nobody nobody that's not going to
be a good environment for anybody but
should I mention names right
now but one of the things you you do
talk about in the book is this concept
of social debt yeah versus just
technical debt and I I assume that that
example you just gave is an example of
that but what what are some other
examples of things that people may not
be obvious to people that this is a
problem when I'm I'm on a team that was
a really interesting concept that I I
dug up uh which is research from a
professor and Germany and he he coined
the term social depth there are lots of
what he calls Community smells instead
of coat smells which are part of the
social adth for instance if you have
what he calls a lone wol in your team
which is this uh person cing away in his
Corner committing stuff not really
discussing anything and just going at it
not really sharing his knowledge that's
obviously a big problem right these
social issues prevent the team from
sharing IDs and from being more creative
so one of the questions you could ask is
yeah of course if there are social
issues in a team it's not going to be
well that performant but what does that
have to do with creative problem
solving well everything I think because
if you don't collaborate you don't share
IDs if you don't share IDs you're not
refining IDs if you don't refine IDs and
have multiple IDs and critically
evaluate each ID then you're just doing
the same thing over and over again and
it's not going to be really great right
other examples Beyond low low move are
like I think it was called information
black hole which is there's lots of
domain knowledge in certain projects
there's lots of technical knowledge but
nobody's writing down anything there's
no internal Wiki there's there's for
instance only fleeting slack messages uh
which are not really collected so if a
few people leave the company and a new
hires come in they have no idea where to
start so that's that's another one it
seems like the examples you gave there
the the first is uh this social aspect
of where you don't feel comfortable to
bring up ideas or try new things because
you feel like they're going to get shot
down or you're going to be scolded so
that really puts a damper on how
creative you can be and then I I suppose
the
the because one of the things you
mentioned earlier was that if you don't
have the the technical knowledge then
you don't really have the information
you need to come up with Creative
Solutions or new Solutions and
so yeah if if everything is just spread
out randomly you don't have access to
the information so you can't get any
insight from it yeah and it's not just
technical knowledge right because you
don't you also have no idea or no clue
what the constraints are about which
constraints have been identified you you
constantly have to poke your your
colleagues and ask them what's what's
this about what's this about what's this
about which means after a few weeks of
of constantly poking they're constantly
out of the zone so their creative state
state of mind is also reduced your
curiosity is reduced because you don't
really feel like asking questions
anymore it's there's no easy way to
access everything so again it's it's
intertwined you you
mentioned curiosity there I wonder if
you can give some examples that you've
had from speaking to other software
developers
about something where their curiosity
really drove them to a no solution or a
creative solution I'll give a simple
example some software development
companies I I think most of them hire
front end software engineers and backend
or full stack or whatever you you can
call them but most of the times there's
a hard split between them you know a few
teams work on the front end it's
decoupled from the apis which are in the
back end the back end might be in go or
in Java whatever in the front end is
usually in Noe or in view s or react or
types skp or whatever and most of these
of course I'm not saying everything
everyone but most people we interviewed
like the front end Engineers they're not
really keen on doing anything in the
back end because you know it's from
those guys you know and and the other
way around but if if you your curiosity
would would Prevail and you would take a
look at what they're doing perhaps one
of those things that they're doing you
know that the for instance Enterprise
design patterns they're applying running
different nodes on different clusters or
just that General concept I'm I'm just
saying something right could be also
could also be applied on on the thing
you're doing right now in the front end
some people I've interviewed said I'm a
Java engineer and I don't want to do
anything with net and that really blows
my mind because I've been doing Java for
six years I've been doing net for five
years
it's the same it's exactly the same you
know the one thing is from Oracle the
other thing is from Microsoft and every
few years net steals something the net C
team steals a syntax from java and the
other way around so I don't really get
why people are so locked into that way
of of programming that's that's a bit
sad I think so that's the lack of
curiosity in in my view so I suppose
it's it's just being open to learning
new things and it also ties a little bit
into I think in your book you mentioned
how in a lot of contexts it's important
to be a generalist in some sense right
to to like you were just saying not just
say I do front-end work so I'm only
going to look at the front end but but
actually be at least somewhat aware of
how the backend Works be able to talk to
those developers have domain knowledge
so that you can basically come up with
better Solutions rather than just
focusing on just one thing yeah and it's
is just a way to generate more insight
that doesn't have to mean that you as a
front-end engineer have to start
developing backend stuff you can have
your preference that's fine but it's
just a way to get more ideas into your
brain and to get started with your front
end stuff or with your back end stuff
whatever but you don't really have to
limit yourself to
Gathering inside from just one specific
subdomain and another thing that you
talk about in your book as this concept
of of critical thinking I I think people
probably have a a vague sense of what
they think that means maybe you could
explain what what it is in your words
well there there's the high level
critical thinking part which is of
course related to lots of psychological
fallacies that we have like biases uh
like confirmation biases or things like
that there's lots and lots and lots of
different things out there regarding
those biases but in context to
creativity there's this creative uh
State diagram so to speak in which you
uh first incubate you have an idea
you're thinking about it you're just
doing something else and your
subconscious is more or less processing
the ID it's it's fermenting in your head
so to speak You're and then you're
participa which means you're doing the
work most of the times it's an illusion
that aha moments happen all of a sudden
90% of the time you're working and 10%
of the time you have those aha moments
but they're linked of course but then
even if you have those two most of the
AHA moments are
crap are really bad bad ideas and you
have to have the proficiency or the tool
set to identify those bad ideas and the
good ideas so there there's got to be
That's What I Call creative thinking in
context of critical thinking in context
of creativity right once you have ideas
which is really cool first ideas have
more ideas the and the purpose of of
being a creative programming is having
more ideas and then second purpose of
being creative program is identifying
and categorizing those ideas is it going
to be a really good idea or is it going
to be a really bad idea
some people are really hard on
themselves and shoot down every ID they
have especially in so-call meetings uh
you know the brainstorm events most of
those events consist of one or two
people just saying this ain't going to
work that's not good that's not good and
that's not a good way to to approach any
idea it might be a bad idea but you
first have to take a really good look at
it and perhaps it's it's a really good
idea yeah so that's the critical
thinking part that comes into play and
are there any examples you came through
in your discussions with people or or
research of where somebody was thinking
of an idea and they weren't sure if it
was a good idea or not and to a lot of
people it may have seemed like not a
good idea but it just was surprising it
actually turned out to be something
really interesting I think one of the
recent ones is for example if you're
working with a uh Legacy software and
there has to be some sort of change but
there's not a lot of time to do it
sometimes there's this brainstorm
session right to to say okay we are on a
tight budget and a tight deadline let's
see what we can do what do you think is
approachable is an approachable way to
to tackle this problem and then most of
the team members I guess write don't
post it and then you start discussing
multiple ideas but most of the time
those things happen at hog which means
you you just blurred out something
without first noting down the ideas and
as soon as you blur out something and
someone shoots down your idea then
you're less likely to to share your
second idea and perhaps that second idea
is the one that the team really really
really needs but again that's also one
of the community smells so to speak uh
if there's one loud mouth which is
constantly doing the talking then the
three people in the back are never going
to say anything so it's up to to
facilitate or to to gather everyone's
ideas before you move on to the critical
thinking part right so that's that's the
recent one I guess yeah so I I suppose
it's maybe deciding that when people
share their ideas publicly that you give
other people time to to see them and
think about them rather than immediately
judging them exactly
yeah
and you sort of mentioned this a little
bit earlier
but when people are thinking through
whether something's a good idea or not
or working through this process of
critical thinking there are assumptions
they can make that kind of leads them
down the wrong path like I think a
example I saw in the book is you you
said there's this first Google hit
coding where you you have a problem you
search and the very first thing you see
you go like okay this is the solution
I'm going to do
this and I wonder if uh you could talk a
little bit to that and the problems with
that as well as other common mistakes I
suppose people make in their critical
thinking yeah one of the really
interesting recent mistakes I see lots
of people doing right now is you know
using co-pilot without really thinking
is this a good implementation
AI is really popular right now to help
so to speak increase the productivity of
programmers but I think it's a bit
overrated because most of the things it
proposes it's supposed to help with
boilerplate code right and not with the
the heavy stuff that you really have to
think about the domain specific critical
stuff and if you just copy paste or or
just say okay I'll accept this proposed
part of of my pattern or the method I'm
working working on on for instance a
switch case statement okay that's good
bam perhaps it's good but not for the
the the problem at hand or in another in
another context it would be good so it's
it pays off to stop and think for a
moment or two is this thing that it's
proposing the right thing to do and if
you don't really know if you're not
really sure then perhaps ask it to a
colleague and not ask ask the AI is this
a good idea
so that's that's a recent one I think um
is really important as as we as these
tools get integrated in the daily
practice of software engineering yeah
the co-pilot example is interesting
because I I hadn't thought of it but
like you said it's almost like the
equivalent of picking the first Google
result right it's rather than it being
ranked first in the search results being
the proof that it's correct it's the
this is what
the large language model gave to me and
that means it's correct and neither of
these things are definitive in terms of
whether they're an actually good
solution or not yeah but most software
Engineers know that they shouldn't
really just copy paste stuff from stack
Overflow I think that joke has passed
but regarding co-pilot since it's new
and shiny and it's it's trained on uh
millions of code bases they think that's
that's the better way to approach it
without applying your own critical
thinking mindset it should still pass
that that mindset flow inside your head
yeah and the the stack Overflow example
I think something about that is that
with stack Overflow you can look at the
the comments other people have left and
the alternative Solutions and I I I find
that that can often help you along in
your thinking through of whether this is
a good solution or is not whereas with
the generated code from say a co-pilot
it's it's presented without context and
so you really have to force yourself to
work a little harder to validate does
this make
sense yeah and one of the new issues
I've seen right now is that part of the
proposed solution from co-pilot gets
pasted into stack Overflow and people
are asking stack Overflow users I've got
this from from C wallet do you think
that's a good
idea so in in effect you're you're
acknowledging that critical thinking
from humans still has to be done but
you're not doing it
yourself and and in the end if you check
code in and it's problematic you can't
just say well it was it's it's copilot's
fault I mean ultimately it was you who
who checked that code in
yeah one of the later things and you've
mentioned this a little bit before for
is this concept of getting into like a
flow state or being in the right State
of Mind for programming and is there
specific things in your research or from
talking to people in terms of what that
state is like and and how you get into
that state yeah I think then we're
approaching the the work of Cal Newport
which is who is a professor at MIT he
going the term deep work and there's
this shallow work which is like
answering mailes attending meetings
sending out slack messagers and then
there's deep work which is concentrated
work really hard thinking doing the
stuff you should really be doing and for
that we could talk a little bit about
the environment because in an open
Office Space where there's lots of
chances for Interruption deep work is
really a big problem why because someone
might approach your desk and ask a
question and then you're somehow
suddenly not in the flow anymore and
research has pointed out that on average
it takes about 20 minutes to get back
into that flow and 20 minutes is a long
time right so once you get once you have
those 20 minutes and you're really back
in the zone and coding at and hacking
away that that one small but really
difficult Problem by then let's say half
an hour passed and another colleague
comes asking a question so if if this
sounds like your typical day then then
there's a problem right then you're
never going to be able to approach a
long stretch of deep work so no really
interesting things ever get done so in
the book I talk a bit about uh ways to
try to mitigate that for instance a
small but stupid thing if you're
interrupted say to the person hold it
one second write out your stream of
thought because you're thinking about
something just type the stuff you're
thinking it shouldn't be braces or it
shouldn't be correct go whatever syntax
you're working on just write out your
stream of thought and then answer the
the person's question when once you get
back to it it'll help you get into that
flow much faster because otherwise you
have something like H what was I doing
again and that thought is lost and in in
that example is it the act of writing
that helps you retain it or is it you go
like after you're done talking to this
other person you go back and read what
you wrote I'll be political and and say
[Laughter]
both writing is a good way to help
retain stuff in your memory right so
when you're preparing for an exam and
you're you're writing stuff you find
interesting in your textbook and you're
summarizing and you're writing with a
pen you know on a piece of paper instead
of the keyboard which is has been proven
to work work even more efficient to
retain that information so yes writing
is an important part but of course when
you're writing down your stream of
thought it has to be quick because the
person is standing next to you so you're
not really going to grab a pen you're
just going to bash a few keystrokes and
then that's done and then there there
there's a rereading indeed that is also
an interesting aspect of trying to get
back into that thought and it depends on
how long it takes between the writing
and the reading how much context you
need to add so if it's just a stream of
thought you're writing down and you're
rereading it within half an hour there's
not a lot of context you need to add but
if it's the end of the work day and
you're going on a vacation of a week or
two weeks and yet then you're going back
then I think it's a better idea to write
a bit more about the context you
know which epic story was I working on
which of the the components did I did I
inspect yesterday or today which things
do I still need to do oh I still need to
ask this to that person those are really
stupid things but they really help once
you get back to get back into the flow
immediately and is that something like
when you worked on teams that you
thought were really effective did you
find that people were writing down these
kinds of things more that they would say
like okay this is where I left off
yesterday and I'm going to pick this up
tomorrow and it's kind of all there or
just curious what your thought is yeah
that's difficult to answer I think
because in most papers regarding the
subject they claim that that that
technique actually works and my personal
experience also says that it does but
I've seen people not doing it and taking
mental notes and they also have no
problems we resuming their daily task I
think it depends on the type of person
you are and
the way you learn I'm a writer and I
like reading and writing and the writing
my own stuff really helps me but I've
also I I know friends who are visual
Learners right so they don't really like
to write in terms of code or words but
for instance they might might make a
small drawing a diagram a floor diagram
a floor chart with a with a small tree
and and a bird and whatever uh but it
helps that helps so again I think it
depends on the context a little bit yeah
and I I suspect this may be somewhat
similar but part of what you mentioned
at the beginning of our conversation was
that in order to have creative output
you need to have technical knowledge you
need to have this base of knowledge to
work off of and for software developers
specifically what are some of the ways
you found that people could effectively
retain knowledge like if I go and watch
a conference talk and maybe I'm watching
the talk and I'm you know this is
interesting and I'm I'm getting it and
then the next day I remember nothing
about what I just watched so I wonder if
you have any thoughts on on retaining
that sort of thing yeah that's really
simple of course I'll say write it down
but again that depends on the person if
you want to write it down using just a
book like I do in an analog and the
fountain pen or digitally in your own
Wiki or your own digital Garden or your
blog online or whatever I guess it also
depends on if you want to publish it
privately or publicly but beyond that
the most important thing is to add
context or if you've seen a conference
talk and you say hm this is interesting
regarding the stuff you're working on
right now if you're writing or you're
summarizing the thing you saw try to
link it to the project you're working on
or to the thing you're working on that
means you're you're starting to connect
things you're just you're not really
just writing down separate isolated
cells or notes or of information but
once you start moving that information
closer together and linking that then
it's that's the part where so to so to
speak the magic
happens yeah and I think the tricky
thing for myself is some sometimes I'll
I'll take notes but there isn't really
any structure I'll just have a whole
bunch of files and there is search so
occasionally I can if I am facing the
same problem I can find it but if I'm
not looking for the right thing it's
kind of just yes it's in there but I
have no idea how to retrieve it yeah
well there there are there are a lot of
digital tools to mitigate that problem
right now one of the most popular ones I
think you might have heard about it is
Obsidian which is actually just a small
layer of software around markdown files
on your own hard drive and it contains
smart searching using the shortcuts that
you're used to work with from Visual
Studio code or from intellig uh so it's
really developer friendly in that sense
it's really easy to publish stuff online
in case you want to do it the
companywide it's really easy to find
stuff uh you can use OCR software you
can check in PDF files it's really crazy
yeah you can easily link stuff but then
you're making those links yourself right
so for instance I learned about go and
I'm currently working on this go project
so these two things should should belong
together but an obsidian obsidian itself
proposes those links if you mention them
implicitly so these are called back
links and these are are the most
interesting ones because sometimes you
don't really make that connection but
the software will say hey maybe this
note you took right there could be
connected to that node you took right
there so the more stuff you throw at it
the more chances something interesting
will be linked together and then of
course it's up to you to make a new note
which is the new knowledge you got from
linking those two yeah that's
interesting I've have used obsidian but
I didn't realize it could infer
the the the topic I suppose of of notes
yeah you've been researching this topic
of creativity and programming and and
ways to get people in a state of mind
and in an environment where software
projects can be successful I wonder
through all this time you've spent are
there any specific like big takeaways
you've had where you felt like okay you
know spent all these years and these are
the things that I I think everybody
should know I suppose that's a really
tough one to answer I think the biggest
takeaway is that creativity is a skill
that can be learned which means everyone
can be creative right I've had a lot of
students come up to me and say I'm not
really that creative I don't really know
how to do this stuff in their mind
they're like I'm not creative and that's
it and of
discussion while for instance they might
also say I'm not a really good Java
developer yet because they know they're
studying software engineering or
computer science and at the end of the
course or within a four or five years in
the industry they'll become a competent
or or perhaps even a good one but they
have this idea of creativity is a set
thing and that's to my view that's
that's incorrect as soon as you start
trying to apply the principles you'll
gradually become better at it it's it's
just like a muscle or it's just like
learning a programming
language yeah and it's also s ties in a
little bit to what you had said where
creativity is is judged by the people
you work with or the people that are
exposed to the things you do and and so
you could be in an environment where
people think like ah what you know what
woter is doing is not creative but but
maybe maybe it's just the wrong audience
right maybe what you're doing it is
creative and it is valuable but the
people just don't see it in that case I
guess it's perhaps time to back your BS
right get your
losses yeah yeah
definitely to kind of wrap up where can
people check out the book and and see
what you're you're up to
next well the book is published by
Manning it's called the creative
programmer so obviously you'll find it
at the product page of Manning itself
and uh as far as myself I have a Blog
called brain baking brain baking.com and
I write
about everything that interests me so I
I like writing about different topics
and linking them in a creative way so
you can also find information about the
book and the content itself on my
website regard ing the survey that we
talked about the creative programming
problem solving test is what we call it
you can find it on brain baking.com
cpps or just on the blog and you search
for it uh you'll find it it's free and
you can just take it and see whether or
not the the reflective questions take
you anywhere all right well woter thank
you so much for chatting with me today
thanks so much for having me it's been
really
interesting this has been Jeremy Jung
for software engineering radio thanks
for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at Team
SE-R doet this and all other episodes of
SC radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening